A Guide to the Powys Family Collection 1968.0001
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Powys Family Collection
1927-1959
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1968.0001
1 Linear Feet
The collection consists of manuscripts and correspondence of four members of the Powys family: (John, Theodore, Laurence (Francis) and Gertrude May (1877-1952); and newsclippings, portraits (sketches), and photographs. Also included is a portfolio of wood engravings by Gertrude. The bulk of the collection concerns John Cowper Powys and was acquired from him by a collector, Rex Parady. This portion of the collection includes correspondence between Powys and Parady in which Powys identifies various manuscripts and other items.
Biography
Theodore Francis Powys
Theodore Francis Powys was born 20 December 1875, in Shirley, England the son of Charles Francis (a clergyman) and Mary Cowper (Johnson) Powys. A farmer, novelist, short story writer and essayist, Powys attended Theodore Francis Powys was born 20 December 1875, in Shirley, England, the son of Charles Francis (a clergyman) and Mary Cowper (Johnson) Powys. A farmer, novelist, short story writer and essayist, Powys attended Dorchester Grammar School. He married Violet Dodds in 1905 and had three children: Charles "Dicky", Francis, and Theodora Gay "Susan" (adopted). Powys died 27 November 1953, in Sturminster Newton (some sources say Mappowder), England, and is buried in Mappowder, England.
John Cowper Powys
Educator, critic, novelist and poet John Cowper Powys was born 8 October 1872, in Shirley, Derbyshire, England, the son of Charles Francis (an Anglican clergyman) and Mary Cowper (Johnson) Powys. He attended Corpus Christi College (M.A.) and was awarded and honorary doctor of letters from University of Wales. Before becoming a writer full-time i in 1934, Powys was a lecturer in literature at Universities in England and the United States (1904-1934, winters). Powys married Margaret Alice Lyon in 1896 (died 1947). They had one son. He died 17 June 1963, in Merionethshire, Wales.
Llewelyn Powys
Llewelyn Powys was born in 1884, the fifth son of Charles Francis (an Anglican clergyman) and Mary Cowper (Johnson) Powys. He died in 1939. [Specific biographical details can be found in the Dictionary of Literary Biography, Volume 98: Modern British Essayists. A Bruccoli Clark Layman Book. Edited by Robert Beum, The Gale Group, 1990. pp. 270-284.]
The largest collections of Powys's papers are in the Everett Needham Case Library, Colgate University, Hamilton, New York; and in the Humanities Research Center, University of Texas at Austin.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of manuscripts and correspondence of four members of the Powys family: (John, Theodore, Laurence (Francis) and Gertrude May (1877-1952); and newsclippings, portraits (sketches), and photographs. Also included is a portfolio of wood engravings by Gertrude. The bulk of the collection concerns John Cowper Powys and was acquired from him by a collector, Rex Parady. This portion of the collection includes correspondence between Powys and Parady in which Powys identifies various manuscripts and other items.
Separated Material
Monographs have been catalogued and information is available through the UConn Library's online catalog, HOMER.
Acquisition Information
Purchased in 1968 from Mr. Parady. Monograph collection was augmented by purchases by the Special Collections Department after acquisition of core collection.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
- Series I: Manuscripts, undated, 1927-1959
  - Powys Family
    - Reviews and articles about, undated, 1942-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Photographs and drawings, undated (Oversize OS, Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Powys, Francis (Laurence)
    - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Powys, Gertrude May
    - Portfolio of engravings, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Powys, John Cowper
    - Correspondence, undated, 1935-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Writings (incomplete)
      - Brazen Head, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Complex Vision, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - [Fragment of a novel], undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Iliad, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - "Preface" to Lawrence Stern, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - "T.F. Powys", undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Up and Out, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Powys, Llewelyn
    - Correspondence and writings, undated, 1927-1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Powys, Theodore Francis
    - Correspondence and writings, undated, 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence and writings about, undated, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Parady, Rex Dennis
    - Correspondence, undated, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 17)